# Ngoc Bui

New Haven, CT, US · (+1) 203-809-4258 ngocbh.pt@gmail.com · ngoc.bui@yale.edu · ngocbh.github.io

# **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

My research interests lie at the intersection of **Machine Learning** (ML) and **Optimization** with a focus on the responsible use of machine learning in real-world systems where humans and high measurement uncertainties exist in the loop.

#### **EDUCATION**

• **Ph.D. in Computer Science**Yale University

2023 – present

• M.S. in Data Science 2021 – 2023

Hanoi University of Science and Technology

- GPA: 3.9/4.0, Major GPA: 4.0/4.0.

• Engineer in Computer Science

Hanoi University of Science and Technology (HUST)

2016 - 2021

- GPA: 3.67/4.0, Major GPA: 3.88/4.0.

- Honors: Excellent (  $\approx$  1st class honors).
- Thesis: A Deep Reinforcement Learning based Online Charging Scheme for Target Coverage and Connectivity in WRSNs.

# **PUBLICATIONS**

- Duy Nguyen, Ngoc Bui, Viet-Anh Nguyen. "Feasible Recourse Plan via Diverse Interpolation". AIS-TATS, 2023.
- Duy Nguyen, Ngoc Bui, Viet-Anh Nguyen. "Distributionally Robust Recourse Action". ICLR, 2023.
- Ngoc Bui, Tam Nguyen, Binh Huynh Thi Thanh, and Trong Vinh Le. "A phenotype-based multiobjective evolutionary algorithm for maximizing lifetime in wireless sensor networks with bounded hop". Soft Computing, 2023.
- Ngoc Bui, Duy Nguyen, Viet-Anh Nguyen. "Counterfactual Plans under Distributional Ambiguity".
   ICLR, 2022.
- Tuan-Duy Hien Nguyen, **Ngoc Bui**, Duy Nguyen, Man-Chung Yue, Viet Anh Nguyen. "Robust Bayesian Recourse". *UAI*, 2022.
- **Ngoc Bui**, Phi Le Nguyen, Viet Anh Nguyen, Phan Thuan Do. "A Deep Reinforcement Learning-based Adaptive Charging Policy for WRSNs". IEEE *MASS*. 2022.
- **Ngoc Bui** and Viet-Trung Tran. "A Novel Conditional Random Fields Aided Fuzzy Matching in Vietnamese Address Standardization". *SoICT*. 2019.

# **UNDER REVIEW**

- **Ngoc Bui**, Hieu Trung Nguyen, Viet Anh Nguyen, and Rex Ying. "Structure-aware Graph Explainer via Myerson-Taylor Interaction Index". Under review.
- Ngoc Bui, Duy Nguyen, Man-Chung Yue, and Viet-Anh Nguyen. "Coverage-Validity-Aware Algorithmic Recourse". Under review.

-

# **EXPERIENCES**

#### • Research Resident

August 2021 - July 2023

Machine Learning group - VinAI Research

- Work under the supervision of Dr. Viet Anh Nguyen, focusing on robust & trustworthy ML, studying different paradigms of explanation methods for machine learning models and their robustness.
- Applied Rotation Project: Interactive Tool for 3D Point Cloud Segmentation.

# • Research Assistant

December 2019 - June 2020

Data Science Lab - HUST

- Study the Vietnamese address standardization problem that recognizes and normalizes free-form addresses into a common standard format.

#### • AI Research Intern

*July 2019 - October 2019* 

IBM Vietnam

- Applying PowerAI Vision to visual inspection problems in the car manufacturing process to detect dirt, and dust defects in the car body after painting.

# **AWARDS & HONORS**

TEACHING		
•	Third prize in Vietnam Olympiad in Informatics.	2016
•	Third prize in ACM/ICPC Asia - Ho Chi Minh Regional.	2017
•	Problem Winner in ASEAN-India Hackathon.	2021
•	Best Thesis Presentation Award.	2021
•	Honorable Mention in INFORMS Undergraduate Operations Research Prize.	2022

# Applied Algorithms classes, HUST PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

2019 - 2021

- Reviewer at AISTATS 2022/2023, FaCCT 2023, UAI 2023, NeuRIPS 2023, ICLR 2024.
- Reviewer at Transactions on Sensor Networks (TOSN).